<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE manualpage SYSTEM "../style/manualpage.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>

<manualpage metafile="index.xml.meta">
  <parentdocument href="../"/>

  <title>How-To / Tutorials</title>

  <section id="howto">

    <title>How-To / Tutorials</title>

    <dl>
      <dt>Authentication</dt>
      <dd>
        <p>Authentication is any process by which you verify that
        someone is who they claim they are. Authorization is any
        process by which someone is allowed to be where they want to
        go, or to have information that they want to have.</p>

        <p>See: <a href="auth.html">Authentication, Authorization, and Access Control</a></p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <dl>
      <dt>Dynamic Content with CGI</dt>
      <dd>
        <p>The CGI (Common Gateway Interface) defines a way for a web
        server to interact with external content-generating programs,
        which are often referred to as CGI programs or CGI scripts. It
        is the simplest, and most common, way to put dynamic content on
        your web site. This document will be an introduction to setting
        up CGI on your Apache web server, and getting started writing
        CGI programs.</p>

        <p>See: <a href="cgi.html">CGI: Dynamic Content</a></p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>.htaccess</code> files</dt>
      <dd>
        <p><code>.htaccess</code> files provide a way to make configuration
        changes on a per-directory basis. A file, containing one or more
        configuration directives, is placed in a particular document directory,
        and the directives apply to that directory, and all subdirectories thereof.</p>

        <p>See: <a href="htaccess.html"><code>.htaccess</code> files</a></p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <dl>
      <dt>Introduction to Server Side Includes</dt>
      <dd>
        <p>SSI (Server Side Includes) are directives that are placed in
        HTML pages, and evaluated on the server while the pages are
        being served. They let you add dynamically generated content to
        an existing HTML page, without having to serve the entire page
        via a CGI program, or other dynamic technology.</p>

        <p>See: <a href="ssi.html">Server Side Includes (SSI)</a></p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <dl>
      <dt>Per-user web directories</dt>
      <dd>
        <p>On systems with multiple users, each user can be permitted to have a
        web site in their home directory using the <directive
        module="mod_userdir">UserDir</directive> directive. Visitors
        to a URL <code>http://example.com/~username/</code> will get content
        out of the home directory of the user "<code>username</code>", out of
        the subdirectory specified by the <directive
        module="mod_userdir">UserDir</directive> directive.</p>

        <p>See: <a href="public_html.html"
        >User web directories (<code>public_html</code>)</a></p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

  </section>

</manualpage>


