<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE modulesynopsis SYSTEM "../style/modulesynopsis.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<!-- $LastChangedRevision: 1330994 $ -->

<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<modulesynopsis metafile="mod_firehose.xml.meta">

<name>mod_firehose</name>
<description>Multiplexes all I/O to a given file or pipe.</description>
<status>Extension</status>
<sourcefile>mod_firehose.c</sourcefile>
<identifier>firehose_module</identifier>

<summary>
    <p><code>mod_firehose</code> provides a mechanism to record data
    being passed between the httpd server and the client at the raw
    connection level to either a file or a pipe in such a way that the
    data can be analysed or played back to the server at a future date.
    It can be thought of as "tcpdump for httpd".</p>

    <p>Connections are recorded after the SSL has been stripped, and can
    be used for forensic debugging.</p>

    <p>The <program>firehose</program> tool can be used to demultiplex
    the recorded stream back into individual files for analysis, or
    playback using a tool like <code>netcat</code>.</p>

    <note><title>WARNING</title>This module IGNORES all request level
    mechanisms to keep data private. It is the responsibility of the
    administrator to ensure that private data is not inadvertently
    exposed using this module.
    </note>

</summary>
<seealso><program>firehose</program></seealso>

<section id="enable">
    <title>Enabling a Firehose</title>

    <p>To enable the module, it should be compiled and loaded
    in to your running Apache configuration, and the directives below
    used to record the data you are interested in.</p>
    
    <p>It is possible to record both incoming and outgoing data to
    the same filename if desired, as the direction of flow is recorded
    within each fragment.</p>

    <p>It is possible to write to both normal files and fifos (pipes).
    In the case of fifos, mod_firehose ensures that the packet size is
    no larger than PIPE_BUF to ensure writes are atomic.</p>

    <p>If a pipe is being used, something must be reading from the pipe
    before httpd is started for the pipe to be successfully opened for
    write. If the request to open the pipe fails, mod_firehose will
    silently stand down and not record anything, and the server will
    keep running as normal.</p>

    <p>By default, all attempts to write will block the server. If the
    webserver has been built against APR v2.0 or later, and an optional
    "nonblock" parameter is specified all file writes will be non
    blocking, and buffer overflows will cause debugging data to be lost.
    In this case it is possible to prioritise the running of the server
    over the recording of firehose data.</p>

</section>

<section id="format">
    <title>Stream Format</title>

    <p>The server typically serves multiple connections simultaneously,
    and as a result requests and responses need to be multiplexed before
    being written to the firehose.</p>
    
    <p>The fragment format is designed as clear text, so that a firehose
    can be opened with and inspected by a normal text editor.
    Alternatively, the <program>firehose</program> tool can be used to
    demultiplex the firehose back into individual requests or
    connections.</p>

    <p>The size of the multiplexed fragments is governed by PIPE_BUF,
    the maximum size of write the system is prepared to perform
    atomically. By keeping the multiplexed fragments below PIPE_BUF in
    size, the module guarantees that data from different fragments does
    not interleave. The size of PIPE_BUF varies on different operating
    systems.</p>

    <p>The BNF for the fragment format is as follows:</p>

    <pre>
 stream = 0*(fragment)

 fragment = header CRLF body CRLF

 header = length SPC timestamp SPC ( request | response ) SPC uuid SPC count

 length = &lt;up to 16 byte hex fragment length>
 timestamp = &lt;up to 16 byte hex timestamp microseconds since 1970>
 request = "&lt;"
 response = ">"
 uuid = &lt;formatted uuid of the connection>
 count = &lt;hex fragment number in the connection>

 body = &lt;the binary content of the fragment>

 SPC = &lt;a single space>
 CRLF = &lt;a carriage return, followed by a line feed>
    </pre>

    <p>All fragments for a connection or a request will share the same
    UUID, depending on whether connections or requests are being recorded.
    If connections are being recorded, multiple requests may appear within
    a connection. A fragment with a zero length indicates the end of the
    connection.</p>

    <p>Fragments may go missing or be dropped if the process reading the
    fragments is too slow. If this happens, gaps will exist in the
    connection counter numbering. A warning will be logged in the error
    log to indicate the UUID and counter of the dropped fragment, so it
    can be confirmed the fragment was dropped.</p>

    <p>It is possible that the terminating empty fragment may not appear,
    caused by the httpd process crashing, or being terminated ungracefully.
    The terminating fragment may be dropped if the process reading the
    fragments is not fast enough.</p>

</section>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseConnectionInput</name>
<description>Capture traffic coming into the server on each connection</description>
<syntax>FirehoseConnectionInput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseConnectionInput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic coming into the server on each connection. Multiple
    requests will be captured within the same connection if keepalive is
    present.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseConnectionInput connection-input.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseConnectionOutput</name>
<description>Capture traffic going out of the server on each connection</description>
<syntax>FirehoseConnectionOutput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseConnectionOutput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic going out of the server on each connection.
    Multiple requests will be captured within the same connection if
    keepalive is present.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseConnectionOutput connection-output.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseRequestInput</name>
<description>Capture traffic coming into the server on each request</description>
<syntax>FirehoseRequestInput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseRequestInput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic coming into the server on each request. Requests
    will be captured separately, regardless of the presence of keepalive.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseRequestInput request-input.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseRequestOutput</name>
<description>Capture traffic going out of the server on each request</description>
<syntax>FirehoseRequestOutput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseRequestOutput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic going out of the server on each request. Requests
    will be captured separately, regardless of the presence of keepalive.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseRequestOutput request-output.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseProxyConnectionInput</name>
<description>Capture traffic coming into the back of mod_proxy</description>
<syntax>FirehoseProxyConnectionInput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseProxyConnectionInput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic being received by mod_proxy.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseProxyConnectionInput proxy-input.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>

<name>FirehoseProxyConnectionOutput</name>
<description>Capture traffic sent out from the back of mod_proxy</description>
<syntax>FirehoseProxyConnectionOutput <var>[ block | nonblock ]</var> <var>filename</var></syntax>
<default>none</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>FirehoseProxyConnectionOutput is only available in Apache 2.5.0 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>Capture traffic being sent out by mod_proxy.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
    <highlight language="config">
      FirehoseProxyConnectionOutput proxy-output.firehose
      </highlight>
    </example>
</usage>

</directivesynopsis>

</modulesynopsis>
