<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE manualpage SYSTEM "../style/manualpage.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<!-- $LastChangedRevision$ -->

<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<manualpage metafile="new_api_2_6.xml.meta">

<title>API Changes in Apache HTTP Server 2.6 since 2.4</title>

<summary>
  <p>This document describes changes to the Apache HTTPD API from
     version 2.4 to 2.6, that may be of interest to module/application
     developers and core hacks.  As of the first GA release of the
     2.6 branch API compatibility is preserved for the life of the
     2.6 branch.  (The
     <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/httpd/httpd/branches/2.6.x/VERSIONING">VERSIONING</a>
     description for the 2.6 release provides more information about API
     compatibility.)</p>

  <p>API changes fall into two categories: APIs that are altogether new,
     and existing APIs that are expanded or changed.  The latter are
     further divided into those where all changes are backwards-compatible
     (so existing modules can ignore them), and those that might
     require attention by maintainers.  As with the transition from
     HTTPD 2.2 to 2.4, existing modules and applications will require
     recompiling and may call for some attention, but most should not
     require any substantial updating (although some may be able to
     take advantage of API changes to offer significant improvements).</p>
  <p>For the purpose of this document, the API is split according
     to the public header files.  These headers are themselves the
     reference documentation, and can be used to generate a browsable
     HTML reference with <code>make docs</code>.</p>
</summary>

<section id="api_changes">
  <title>Changed APIs</title>

  <section id="ap_fill_me_in">
    <title>ap_fill_me_in (NEW!)</title>
    <p>Introduces a new API to fill me in.</p>
  </section>

</section>

<section id="upgrading">
  <title>Specific information on upgrading modules from 2.4</title>

  <section id="upgrading_fillmein">
    <title>Fill me in</title>
    <p>In order to take advantage of fill me in.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrading_byfunction">
    <title>If your module uses these existing APIs...</title>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>ap_md5digest()</code> / <code>ap_md5contextTo64</code></dt>
      <dd>These functions are no longer available. Use the equivalent functions
          from APR if needed.</dd>

    </dl>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrading_byfeature">
    <title>If your module interfaces with this feature...</title>
    <dl>
      <dt>fillmin</dt>
      <dd>Optional: If your module fills me in.</dd>

    </dl>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrading_newfeatures">
    <title>Does your module...</title>
    <dl>
    <dt>Fill me in</dt>
    <dd>Consider if filling me in.</dd>

    </dl>
  </section>

</section>

</manualpage>
