<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE modulesynopsis SYSTEM "../style/modulesynopsis.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.5 $ -->

<!--
 Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation

 Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<modulesynopsis metafile="mod_filter.xml.meta">

<name>mod_filter</name>
<description>Context-sensitive smart filter configuration module</description>
<status>Extension</status>
<sourcefile>mod_filter.c</sourcefile>
<identifier>filter_module</identifier>
<compatibility>Version 2.1 and higher</compatibility>

<summary>
    <p>This module enables smart, context-sensitive configuration of
    output content filters.  For example, apache can be configured to
    process different content-types through different filters, even
    when the content-type is not known in advance (e.g. in a proxy).</p>

    <p>mod_filter works by introducing indirection into the filter
    chain.  Instead of inserting filters in the chain, we insert
    a filter harness which in turn dispatches conditionally
    to a filter provider.  Any content filter may be used as a provider
    to mod_filter; no change to existing filter modules is required
    (although it may be possible to simplify them).</p>
</summary>

<section id="smart"><title>Smart Filtering</title>
    <p>In the traditional filtering model, filters are inserted unconditionally
    using <directive module="mod_mime">AddOutputFilter</directive> and family.
    Each filter then needs to determine whether to run, and there is little
    flexibility available for server admins to allow the chain to be
    configured dynamically.</p>

    <p>mod_filter by contrast gives server administrators a great deal of
    flexibility in configuring the filter chain.  In fact, filters can be
    inserted based on any Request Header, Response Header or Environment
    Variable.  This generalises the limited flexibility offered by
    <directive module="core">AddOutputFilterByType</directive>, and fixes
    it to work correctly with dynamic content, regardless of the
    content generator.  The ability to dispatch based on Environment
    Variables offers the full flexibility of configuration with
    <module>mod_rewrite</module> to anyone who needs it.</p>
</section>

<section id="terms"><title>Filter Declarations, Providers and Chains</title>
    <p class="figure">
    <img src="../images/mod_filter_old.gif" width="160" height="310"
    alt="[This image displays the traditional filter model]"/><br />
    <dfn>Figure 1:</dfn> The traditional filter model</p>

    <p>In the traditional model, output filters are a simple chain
    from the content generator (handler) to the client.  This works well
    provided the filter chain can be correctly configured, but presents
    problems when the filters need to be configured dynamically based on
    the outcome of the handler.</p>

    <p class="figure">
    <img src="../images/mod_filter_new.gif" width="423" height="331"
    alt="[This image shows the mod_filter model]"/><br />
    <dfn>Figure 2:</dfn> The <module>mod_filter</module> model</p>

    <p>mod_filter works by introducing indirection into the filter
    chain.  Instead of inserting filters in the chain, we insert
    a filter harness which in turn dispatches conditionally
    to a filter provider.  Any content filter may be used as a provider
    to mod_filter; no change to existing filter modules is required
    (although it may be possible to simplify them).  There can be
    multiple providers for one filter, but no more than one provider will
    run for any single request.</p>

    <p>A filter chain comprises any number of instances of the filter
    harness, each of which may have any number of providers.  A special
    case is that of a single provider with unconditional dispatch: this
    is equivalent to inserting the provider filter directly into the chain.</p>
</section>

<section id="config"><title>Configuring the Chain</title>
    <p>There are three stages to configuring a filter chain with mod_filter.
    For details of the directives, see below.</p>

    <dl>
    <dt>Declare Filters</dt>
    <dd>The <directive>FilterDeclare</directive> directive declares a filter,
    assigning it a name and a dispatch criterion.</dd>

    <dt>Register Providers</dt>
    <dd>The <directive>FilterProvider</directive> directive registers a
    provider with a filter. The filter must have been registered with
    <directive>FilterDeclare</directive>. The provider must have been
    registered with <code>ap_register_output_filter</code> by some module.
    The final argument to <directive>FilterProvider</directive> is a match
    string, that will be checked against the filter's dispatch criterion
    to determine whether to run this provider.</dd>

    <dt>Configure the Chain</dt>
    <dd>The above directives build components of a smart filter chain,
    but do not configure it to run.  The <directive>FilterChain</directive>
    directive builds a filter chain from smart filters declared, offering the
    flexibility to insert filters at the beginning or end of the chain,
    remove a filter, or clear the chain.</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section id="examples"><title>Examples</title>
    <dl>
    <dt>Server side Includes (SSI)</dt>
    <dd>A simple case of using mod_filter in place of
    <directive module="core">AddOutputFilterByType</directive>
    <example>
      FilterDeclare SSI Content-Type<br/>
      FilterProvider SSI INCLUDES $text/html<br/>
      FilterChain SSI
    </example>
    </dd>

    <dt>Server side Includes (SSI)</dt>
    <dd>The same as the above but dispatching on handler (classic
    SSI behaviour; .shtml files get processed).
    <example>
      FilterDeclare SSI Handler<br/>
      FilterProvider SSI INCLUDES server-parsed<br/>
      FilterChain SSI
    </example>
    </dd>

    <dt>Emulating mod_gzip with mod_deflate</dt>
    <dd>Insert INFLATE filter only if "gzip" is NOT in the
    Accept-Encoding header.
    <example>
      FilterDeclare gzip req=Accept-Encoding<br/>
      FilterProvider gzip inflate !$gzip<br/>
      FilterChain gzip
    </example>
    </dd>

    <dt>Image Downsampling</dt>
    <dd>Suppose we want to downsample all web images, and have filters
    for GIF, JPEG and PNG.
    <example>
      FilterDeclare unpack Content-Type<br/>
      FilterProvider unpack jpeg_unpack $image/jpeg<br/>
      FilterProvider unpack gif_unpack $image/gif<br/>
      FilterProvider unpack png_unpack $image/png<br/>
      <br />
      FilterDeclare downsample Content-Type<br/>
      FilterProvider downsample downsample_filter $image<br/>
      FilterProtocol downsample "change=yes"<br/>
      <br />
      FilterDeclare repack Content-Type<br/>
      FilterProvider repack jpeg_pack $image/jpeg<br/>
      FilterProvider repack gif_pack $image/gif<br/>
      FilterProvider repack png_pack $image/png<br/>
      &lt;Location /image-filter&gt;<br/>
      <indent>
        FilterChain unpack downsample repack<br/>
      </indent>
      &lt;/Location&gt;
    </example>
    </dd>
    </dl>
</section>

<section id="protocol"><title>Protocol Handling</title>
    <p>Historically, each filter is responsible for ensuring that whatever
    changes it makes are correctly represented in the HTTP response headers,
    and that it does not run when it would make an illegal change.  This
    imposes a burden on filter authors to re-implement some common
    functionality in every filter:</p>

    <ul>
    <li>Many filters will change the content, invalidating existing content
    tags, checksums, hashes, and lengths.</li>

    <li>Filters that require an entire, unbroken response in input need to
    ensure they don't get byteranges from a backend.</li>

    <li>Filters that transform output in a filter need to ensure they don't
    violate a <code>Cache-Control: no-transform</code> header from the
    backend.</li>

    <li>Filters may make responses uncacheable.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>mod_filter aims to offer generic handling of these details of filter
    implementation, reducing the complexity required of content filter modules.
    This is work-in-progress; the <directive>FilterProtocol</directive>
    implements some of this functionality, but there are no API calls yet.</p>

    <p>At the same time, mod_filter should not interfere with a filter that
    wants to handle all aspects of the protocol.  By default (i.e. in the
    absence of any <directive>FilterProtocol</directive> directives), mod_filter
    will leave the headers untouched.</p>
</section>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>FilterDeclare</name>
<description>Declare a smart filter</description>
<syntax>FilterDeclare <var>filter-name</var> [req|resp|env]=<var>dispatch</var>
<var>[type]</var>
</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>This directive declares an output filter together with a
    header or environment variable that will determine runtime
    configuration.  The first argument is a <code>filter-name</code>
    for use in <directive>FilterProvider</directive>,
    <directive>FilterChain</directive> and
    <directive>FilterProtocol</directive> directives.</p>

    <p>The second is a string with optional <code>req=</code>,
    <code>resp=</code> or <code>env=</code> prefix causing it
    to dispatch on (respectively) the request header, response
    header, or environment variable named.  In the absence of a
    prefix, it defaults to a response header.  A special case is the
    word "handler", which causes mod_filter to dispatch on the handler.</p>

    <p>The final (optional) argument
    is the type of filter, and takes values of <var>ap_filter_type</var>
    - namely <var>RESOURCE</var> (the default), <var>CONTENT_SET</var>,
    <var>PROTOCOL</var>, <var>TRANSCODE</var>, <var>CONNECTION</var>
    or <var>NETWORK</var>.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>FilterProvider</name>
<description>Register a content filter</description>
<syntax>FilterProvider <var>filter-name</var> <var>provider-name</var>
    <var>match</var></syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>This directive registers a <em>provider</em> for the smart filter.
    The provider will be called if and only if the <var>match</var> declared
    here matches the value of the header or environment variable declared
    as <var>dispatch</var> in the <directive>FilterDeclare</directive>
    directive that declared <var>filter-name</var>.</p>

    <p><var>filter-name</var> must have been declared with 
    <directive>FilterDeclare</directive>.  <var>provider-name</var> must have
    been registered by loading a module that registers the name with
    <code>ap_register_output_filter</code>.</p>

    <p>The <var>match</var> argument specifies a match that will be applied to
    the filter's <var>dispatch</var> criterion.  The match may be a string
    match (exact match or substring), a regexp, an integer (greater, lessthan
    or equals), or unconditional.  The first characters of the <var>match</var>
    argument determines this:</p>

    <p><strong>First</strong>, if the first character is an exclamation mark
    <strong>!</strong>, this reverses the rule, so the provider will be used
    if and only if the match <em>fails</em>.</p>

    <p><strong>Second</strong>, it interprets the first character excluding
    any leading ! as follows:</p>

    <dl>
    <dt>default</dt>
    <dd>exact match</dd>

    <dt>$</dt>
    <dd>substring match</dd>

    <dt>/</dt>
    <dd>regexp match</dd>

    <dt>=</dt>
    <dd>integer equality</dd>

    <dt>&lt;</dt>
    <dd>integer less-than</dd>

    <dt>&gt;</dt>
    <dd>integer greater-than</dd>

    <dt>*</dt>
    <dd>Unconditional match</dd>
    </dl>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>FilterChain</name>
<description>Configure the filter chain</description>
<syntax>FilterChain ([+=-@!]<var>filter-name</var>)+</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>This configures an actual filter chain, from declared filters.
    <directive>FilterChain</directive> takes any number of arguments,
    each optionally preceded with a single-character control that
    determines what to do:</p>

    <dl>
    <dt>+filter-name</dt>
    <dd>Add filter-name to the end of the filter chain</dd>

    <dt>@filter-name</dt>
    <dd>Insert filter-name at the start of the filter chain</dd>

    <dt>-filter-name</dt>
    <dd>Remove filter-name from the filter chain</dd>

    <dt>=filter-name</dt>
    <dd>Empty the filter chain and insert filter-name</dd>

    <dt>!</dt>
    <dd>Empty the filter chain</dd>

    <dt>filter-name</dt>
    <dd>Equivalent to +filter-name</dd>
    </dl>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>FilterProtocol</name>
<description>Deal with correct HTTP protocol handling</description>
<syntax>FilterProtocol filter-name [provider-name] "proto-flags"</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>This directs mod_filter to deal with ensuring the filter doesn't run
    when it shouldn't, and that the HTTP response headers are correctly set
    taking into account the effects of the filter.</p>

    <p>There are two forms of this directive.  With three arguments, it
    applies specifically to a filter-name and a provider for that filter.
    With two arguments it applies to a filter-name whenever the filter runs
    <em>any</em> provider.</p>

    <p><var>proto-flags</var> is one or more of</p>

    <dl>
    <dt>change=yes</dt>
    <dd>The filter changes the content, including possibly the content
    length</dd>

    <dt>change=1:1</dt>
    <dd>The filter changes the content, but will not change the content
    length</dd>

    <dt>byteranges=no</dt>
    <dd>The filter cannot work on byteranges and requires complete input</dd>

    <dt>proxy=no</dt>
    <dd>The filter should not run in a proxy context</dd>

    <dt>proxy=transform</dt>
    <dd>The filter transforms the response in a manner incompatible with
    the HTTP <code>Cache-Control: no-transform</code> header.</dd>

    <dt>cache=no</dt>
    <dd>The filter renders the output uncacheable (eg by introducing randomised
    content changes)</dd>
    </dl>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>FilterTrace</name>
<description>Get debug/diagnostic information from mod_filter</description>
<syntax>FilterTrace filter-name level</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>This directive generates debug information from mod_filter.
    It is designed to help test and debug providers (filter modules), although
    it may also help with mod_filter itself.</p>

    <p>The debug output depends on the level set:</p>
    <dl>
    <dt>0 (default)</dt>
    <dd>No debug information is generated.</dd>

    <dt>1</dt>
    <dd>mod_filter will record buckets and brigades passing through the filter
    to the error log, before the provider has processed them.
    This is similar to the information generated by
    <a href="http://apache.webthing.com/mod_diagnostics/">mod_diagnostics</a>.
    </dd>

    <dt>2 (not yet implemented)</dt>
    <dd>Will dump the full data passing through to a tempfile before the
    provider. <strong>For single-user debug only</strong>; this will not
    support concurrent hits.</dd>
    </dl>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

</modulesynopsis>

