<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE modulesynopsis SYSTEM "../style/modulesynopsis.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<modulesynopsis metafile="mod_mime.xml.meta">

<name>mod_mime</name>
<description>Associates the requested filename's extensions
    with the file's behavior (handlers and filters)
    and content (mime-type, language, character set and
    encoding)</description>
<status>Base</status>
<sourcefile>mod_mime.c</sourcefile>
<identifier>mime_module</identifier>

<summary>
    <p>This module is used to associate various bits of "meta
    information" with files by their filename extensions. This
    information relates the filename of the document to it's
    mime-type, language, character set and encoding. This
    information is sent to the browser, and participates in content
    negotiation, so the user's preferences are respected when
    choosing one of several possible files to serve. See
    <module>mod_negotiation</module> for more information
    about <a href="../content-negotiation.html">content negotiation</a>.</p>

    <p>The directives <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddCharset</directive>, <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddEncoding</directive>, <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddLanguage</directive> and <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddType</directive> are all used to map file
    extensions onto the meta-information for that file. Respectively
    they set the character set, content-encoding, content-language,
    and MIME-type (content-type) of documents.  The directive <directive
    module="mod_mime">TypesConfig</directive> is used to specify a
    file which also maps extensions onto MIME types. </p>

    <p>In addition, <module>mod_mime</module> may define the <a
    href="../handler.html">handler</a> and <a
    href="../filter.html">filters</a> that originate and process
    content.  The directives <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddHandler</directive>, <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddOutputFilter</directive>, and <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddInputFilter</directive> control the modules
    or scripts that serve the document.  The <directive
    module="mod_mime">MultiviewsMatch</directive> directive allows
    <module>mod_negotiation</module> to consider these file extensions
    to be included when testing Multiviews matches.</p>

    <p>While <module>mod_mime</module> associates meta-information
    with filename extensions, the <module>core</module> server
    provides directives that are used to associate all the files in a
    given container (<em>e.g.</em>, <directive type="section"
    module="core">Location</directive>, <directive type="section"
    module="core">Directory</directive>, or <directive type="section"
    module="core">Files</directive>) with particular
    meta-information. These directives include <directive
    module="core">ForceType</directive>, <directive
    module="core">SetHandler</directive>, <directive
    module="core">SetInputFilter</directive>, and <directive
    module="core">SetOutputFilter</directive>.  The core directives
    override any filename extension mappings defined in
    <module>mod_mime</module>.</p>

    <p>Note that changing the meta-information for a file does not
    change the value of the <code>Last-Modified</code> header.
    Thus, previously cached copies may still be used by a client or
    proxy, with the previous headers. If you change the
    meta-information (language, content type, character set or
    encoding) you may need to 'touch' affected files (updating
    their last modified date) to ensure that all visitors are
    receive the corrected content headers.</p>
</summary>
<seealso><directive
module="mod_mime_magic">MimeMagicFile</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">AddDefaultCharset</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">ForceType</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">DefaultType</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetHandler</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetInputFilter</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetOutputFilter</directive></seealso>

<section id="multipleext"><title>Files with Multiple Extensions</title>
    <p>Files can have more than one extension, and the order of the
    extensions is <em>normally</em> irrelevant. For example, if the
    file <code>welcome.html.fr</code> maps onto content type
    <code>text/html</code> and language French then the file
    <code>welcome.fr.html</code> will map onto exactly the same information.
    If more than one extension is given which maps onto the same
    type of meta-information, then the one to the right will be
    used. For example, if <code>.gif</code> maps to the MIME-type
    <code>image/gif</code> and <code>.html</code> maps to the MIME-type
    <code>text/html</code>, then the file <code>welcome.gif.html</code>
    will be associated with the MIME-type <code>text/html</code>.</p>

    <p>Care should be taken when a file with multiple extensions
    gets associated with both a MIME-type and a handler. This will
    usually result in the request being by the module associated
    with the handler. For example, if the <code>.imap</code>
    extension is mapped to the handler <code>imap-file</code> (from
    <module>mod_imap</module>) and the <code>.html</code> extension is
    mapped to the MIME-type <code>text/html</code>, then the file
    <code>world.imap.html</code> will be associated with both the
    <code>imap-file</code> handler and <code>text/html</code> MIME-type.
    When it is processed, the <code>imap-file</code> handler will be used,
    and so it will be treated as a <module>mod_imap</module> imagemap
    file.</p>
</section>

<section id="contentencoding"><title>Content encoding</title>
    <p>A file of a particular MIME type can additionally be encoded a
    particular way to simplify transmission over the Internet.
    While this usually will refer to compression, such as
    <code>gzip</code>, it can also refer to encryption, such a
    <code>pgp</code> or to an encoding such as UUencoding, which is
    designed for transmitting a binary file in an ASCII (text)
    format.</p>

    <p>The <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt">HTTP/1.1
    RFC</a>, section 14.11 puts it this way:</p>

    <blockquote cite="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt">
      <p>The Content-Encoding entity-header field is used as a modifier to
      the media-type. When present, its value indicates what additional
      content codings have been applied to the entity-body, and thus what
      decoding mechanisms must be applied in order to obtain the media-type
      referenced by the Content-Type header field. Content-Encoding is
      primarily used to allow a document to be compressed without losing
      the identity of its underlying media type.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>By using more than one file extension (see <a
    href="#multipleext">section above about multiple file
    extensions</a>), you can indicate that a file is of a
    particular <em>type</em>, and also has a particular
    <em>encoding</em>. </p>

    <p>For example, you may have a file which is a Microsoft Word
    document, which is pkzipped to reduce its size. If the
    <code>.doc</code> extension is associated with the Microsoft
    Word file type, and the <code>.zip</code> extension is
    associated with the pkzip file encoding, then the file
    <code>Resume.doc.zip</code>would be known to be a pkzip'ed Word
    document.</p>

    <p>Apache sends a <code>Content-encoding</code> header with the
    resource, in order to tell the client browser about the
    encoding method.</p>

    <example>Content-encoding: pkzip</example>
</section>

<section id="charset-lang"><title>Character sets and languages</title>
    <p>In addition to file type and the file encoding,
    another important piece of information is what language a
    particular document is in, and in what character set the file
    should be displayed. For example, the document might be written
    in the Vietnamese alphabet, or in Cyrillic, and should be
    displayed as such. This information, also, is transmitted in
    HTTP headers.</p>

    <p>The character set, language, encoding and mime type are all 
    used in the process of content negotiation (See 
    <module>mod_negotiation</module>) to determine
    which document to give to the client, when there are
    alternative documents in more than one character set, language, 
    encoding or mime type. All filename extensions associations
    created with <directive module="mod_mime">AddCharset</directive>,
    <directive module="mod_mime">AddEncoding</directive>, <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddLanguage</directive> and <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddType</directive> directives
    (and extensions listed in the <directive module="mod_mime_magic"
    >MimeMagicFile</directive>) participate in this select process.
    Filename extensions that are only associated using the <directive
    module="mod_mime">AddHandler</directive>, <directive module="mod_mime"
    >AddInputFilter</directive> or <directive module="mod_mime"
    >AddOutputFilter</directive> directives may be included or excluded
    from matching by using the <directive module="mod_mime"
    >MultiviewsMatch</directive> directive.</p>

    <section id="charset"><title>Charset</title>
      <p>To convey this further information, Apache optionally sends
      a <code>Content-Language</code> header, to specify the language
      that the document is in, and can append additional information
      onto the <code>Content-Type</code> header to indicate the
      particular character set that should be used to correctly
      render the information.</p>

      <example>
        Content-Language: en, fr<br />
	Content-Type: text/plain; charset=ISO-8859-1
      </example>

      <p>The language specification is the two-letter abbreviation
      for the language. The <code>charset</code> is the name of the
      particular character set which should be used.</p>
    </section>
</section>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddCharset</name>
<description>Maps the given filename extensions to the specified content
charset</description>
<syntax>AddCharset <var>charset</var> <var>extension</var>
[<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>AddCharset</directive> directive maps the given
    filename extensions to the specified content charset. <var>charset</var>
    is the MIME charset parameter of filenames containing
    <var>extension</var>. This mapping is added to any already in force,
    overriding any mappings that already exist for the same
    <var>extension</var>.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      AddLanguage ja .ja<br />
      AddCharset EUC-JP .euc<br />
      AddCharset ISO-2022-JP .jis<br />
      AddCharset SHIFT_JIS .sjis
    </example>

    <p>Then the document <code>xxxx.ja.jis</code> will be treated
    as being a Japanese document whose charset is <code>ISO-2022-JP</code>
    (as will the document <code>xxxx.jis.ja</code>). The
    <directive>AddCharset</directive> directive is useful for both to
    inform the client about the character encoding of the document so that
    the document can be interpreted and displayed appropriately, and for <a
    href="../content-negotiation.html">content negotiation</a>,
    where the server returns one from several documents based on
    the client's charset preference.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><module>mod_negotiation</module></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">AddDefaultCharset</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddEncoding</name>
<description>Maps the given filename extensions to the specified encoding
type</description>
<syntax>AddEncoding <var>MIME-enc</var> <var>extension</var>
[<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>AddEncoding</directive> directive maps the given
    filename extensions to the specified encoding type. <var>MIME-enc</var>
    is the MIME encoding to use for documents containing the
    <var>extension</var>. This mapping is added to any already in force,
    overriding any mappings that already exist for the same
    <var>extension</var>.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      AddEncoding x-gzip .gz<br />
      AddEncoding x-compress .Z
    </example>

    <p>This will cause filenames containing the <code>.gz</code> extension
    to be marked as encoded using the <code>x-gzip</code> encoding, and
    filenames containing the <code>.Z</code> extension to be marked as
    encoded with <code>x-compress</code>.</p>

    <p>Old clients expect <code>x-gzip</code> and <code>x-compress</code>,
    however the standard dictates that they're equivalent to
    <code>gzip</code> and <code>compress</code> respectively. Apache does
    content encoding comparisons by ignoring any leading <code>x-</code>.
    When responding with an encoding Apache will use whatever form
    (<em>i.e.</em>, <code>x-foo</code> or <code>foo</code>) the
    client requested. If the client didn't specifically request a
    particular form Apache will use the form given by the
    <code>AddEncoding</code> directive. To make this long story
    short, you should always use <code>x-gzip</code> and
    <code>x-compress</code> for these two specific encodings. More
    recent encodings, such as <code>deflate</code> should be
    specified without the <code>x-</code>.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddHandler</name>
<description>Maps the filename extensions to the specified
handler</description>
<syntax>AddHandler <var>handler-name</var> <var>extension</var>
[<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>Files having the name <var>extension</var> will be served by the
    specified <var><a href="../handler.html">handler-name</a></var>. This
    mapping is added to any already in force, overriding any mappings that
    already exist for the same <var>extension</var>. For example, to
    activate CGI scripts with the file extension <code>.cgi</code>, you
    might use:</p>

    <example>
      AddHandler cgi-script .cgi
    </example>

    <p>Once that has been put into your httpd.conf file, any file containing
    the <code>.cgi</code> extension will be treated as a CGI program.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetHandler</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddInputFilter</name>
<description>Maps filename extensions to the filters that will process
client requests</description>
<syntax>AddInputFilter <var>filter</var>[;<var>filter</var>...]
<var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>AddInputFilter is only available in Apache 2.0.26 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p><directive>AddInputFilter</directive> maps the filename extension
    <var>extension</var> to the <a href="../filter.html">filters</a> which
    will process client requests and POST input when they are received by
    the server. This is in addition to any filters defined elsewhere,
    including the <directive module="core">SetInputFilter</directive>
    directive. This mapping is merged over any already in force, overriding
    any mappings that already exist for the same <var>extension</var>.</p>

    <p>If more than one filter is specified, they must be separated
    by semicolons in the order in which they should process the
    content. Both the filter and <var>extension</var> arguments are
    case-insensitive, and the extension may be specified with or
    without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="mod_mime">RemoveInputFilter</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetInputFilter</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddLanguage</name>
<description>Maps the given filename extension to the specified content
language</description>
<syntax>AddLanguage <var>MIME-lang</var> <var>extension</var>
[<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>AddLanguage</directive> directive maps the given
    filename extension to the specified content language.
    <var>MIME-lang</var> is the MIME language of filenames containing
    <var>extension</var>. This mapping is added to any already in force,
    overriding any mappings that already exist for the same
    <var>extension</var>.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      AddEncoding x-compress .Z<br />
      AddLanguage en .en<br />
      AddLanguage fr .fr
    </example>

    <p>Then the document <code>xxxx.en.Z</code> will be treated as
    being a compressed English document (as will the document
    <code>xxxx.Z.en</code>). Although the content language is
    reported to the client, the browser is unlikely to use this
    information. The <directive>AddLanguage</directive> directive is
    more useful for <a href="../content-negotiation.html">content
    negotiation</a>, where the server returns one from several documents
    based on the client's language preference.</p>

    <p>If multiple language assignments are made for the same
    extension, the last one encountered is the one that is used.
    That is, for the case of:</p>

    <example>
      AddLanguage en .en<br />
      AddLanguage en-uk .en<br />
      AddLanguage en-us .en
    </example>

    <p>documents with the extension <code>.en</code> would be treated as
    being <code>en-us</code>.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><module>mod_negotiation</module></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddOutputFilter</name>
<description>Maps filename extensions to the filters that will process
responses from the server</description>
<syntax>AddOutputFilter <var>filter</var>[;<var>filter</var>...]
<var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>AddOutputFilter is only available in Apache 2.0.26 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>AddOutputFilter</directive> directive maps the
    filename extension <var>extension</var> to the <a
    href="../filter.html">filters</a> which will process responses
    from the server before they are sent to the client. This is in
    addition to any filters defined elsewhere, including <directive
    module="core">SetOutputFilter</directive> and <directive module="core"
    >AddOutputFilterByType</directive> directive. This mapping is merged
    over any already in force, overriding any mappings that already exist
    for the same <var>extension</var>.</p>

    <p>For example, the following configuration will process all
    <code>.shtml</code> files for server-side includes and will then
    compress the output using <module>mod_deflate</module>.</p>

    <example>
      AddOutputFilter INCLUDES;DEFLATE shtml
    </example>

    <p>If more than one filter is specified, they must be separated
    by semicolons in the order in which they should process the
    content. Both the <var>filter</var> and <var>extension</var> arguments
    are case-insensitive, and the extension may be specified with or
    without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="mod_mime">RemoveOutputFilter</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetOutputFilter</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AddType</name>
<description>Maps the given filename extensions onto the specified content
type</description>
<syntax>AddType <var>MIME-type</var> <var>extension</var>
[<var>extension</var>] ...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>AddType</directive> directive maps the given filename
    extensions onto the specified content type. <var>MIME-type</var> is the
    MIME type to use for filenames containing <var>extension</var>. This
    mapping is added to any already in force, overriding any mappings that
    already exist for the same <var>extension</var>. This directive can
    be used to add mappings not listed in the MIME types file (see the
    <directive module="mod_mime">TypesConfig</directive> directive).</p>
    
    <example><title>Example</title>
      AddType image/gif .gif
    </example>

    <note>
      It is recommended that new MIME types be added using the
      <directive>AddType</directive> directive rather than changing the 
      <directive module="mod_mime">TypesConfig</directive> file.
    </note>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="core">DefaultType</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">ForceType</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>MultiviewsMatch</name>
<description>The types of files that will be included when searching for
a matching file with MultiViews</description>
<syntax>MultiviewsMatch Any|NegotiatedOnly|Filters|Handlers
[Handlers|Filters]</syntax>
<default>MultiviewsMatch NegotiatedOnly</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>Available in Apache 2.0.26 and later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p><directive>MultiviewsMatch</directive> permits three different
    behaviors for <a href="mod_negotiation.html">mod_negotiation</a>'s
    Multiviews feature.  Multiviews allows a request for a file,
    <em>e.g.</em> <code>index.html</code>, to match any negotiated
    extensions following the base request, <em>e.g.</em>
    <code>index.html.en</code>, <code>index.html.fr</code>, or
    <code>index.html.gz</code>.</p>

    <p>The <code>NegotiatedOnly</code> option provides that every extension
    following the base name must correlate to a recognized
    <module>mod_mime</module> extension for content negotation, <em>e.g.</em>
    Charset, Content-Type, Language, or Encoding.  This is the strictest
    implementation with the fewest unexpected side effects, and is the
    default behavior.</p>

    <p>To include extensions associated with Handlers and/or Filters,
    set the <directive>MultiviewsMatch</directive> directive to either
    <code>Handlers</code>, <code>Filters</code>, or both option keywords.
    If all other factors are equal, the smallest file will be served,
    <em>e.g.</em> in deciding between <code>index.html.cgi</code> of 500
    bytes and <code>index.html.pl</code> of 1000 bytes, the <code>.cgi</code>
    file would win in this example. Users of <code>.asis</code> files
    might prefer to use the Handler option, if <code>.asis</code> files are
    associated with the <code>asis-handler</code>.</p>

    <p>You may finally allow <code>Any</code> extensions to match, even if
    <module>mod_mime</module> doesn't recognize the extension. This was the
    behavior in Apache 1.3, and can cause unpredicatable results, such as
    serving .old or .bak files the webmaster never expected to be served.</p>

    <p>For example, the following configuration will allow handlers
    and filters to participate in Multviews, but will exclude unknown
    files:</p>

    <example>
      MultiviewsMatch Handlers Filters
    </example>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="core">Options</directive></seealso>
<seealso><module>mod_negotiation</module></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>DefaultLanguage</name>
<description>Sets all files in the given scope to the specified
language</description>
<syntax>DefaultLanguage <var>MIME-lang</var></syntax>
<contextlist><context>server config</context><context>virtual host</context>
<context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>DefaultLanguage</directive> directive tells Apache
    that all files in the directive's scope (<em>e.g.</em>, all files
    covered by the current <directive module="core" type="section"
    >Directory</directive> container) that don't have an explicit language
    extension (such as <code>.fr</code> or <code>.de</code> as configured
    by <directive module="mod_mime">AddLanguage</directive>) should be
    considered to be in the specified <var>MIME-lang</var> language. This
    allows entire directories to be marked as containing Dutch content, for
    instance, without having to rename each file. Note that unlike using
    extensions to specify languages, <directive>DefaultLanguage</directive>
    can only specify a single language.</p>

    <p>If no <directive>DefaultLanguage</directive> directive is in force,
    and a file does not have any language extensions as configured
    by <directive module="mod_mime">AddLanguage</directive>, then that file
    will be considered to have no language attribute.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      DefaultLanguage en
    </example>
</usage>
<seealso><module>mod_negotiation</module></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>ModMimeUsePathInfo</name>
<description>Tells <module>mod_mime</module> to treat <code>path_info</code>
components as part of the filename</description>
<syntax>ModMimeUsePathInfo On|Off</syntax>
<default>ModMimeUsePathInfo Off</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context></contextlist>
<compatibility>Available in Apache 2.0.41 and later</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>ModMimeUsePathInfo</directive> directive is used to
    combine the filename with the <code>path_info</code> URL component to
    apply <module>mod_mime</module>'s directives to the request. The default
    value is <code>Off</code> - therefore, the <code>path_info</code>
    component is ignored.</p>

    <p>This directive is recommended when you have a virtual filesystem.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      ModMimeUsePathInfo On
    </example>

    <p>If you have a request for <code>/bar/foo.shtml</code> where
    <code>/bar</code> is a Location and <directive
    >ModMimeUsePathInfo</directive> is <code>On</code>,
    <module>mod_mime</module> will treat the incoming request as
    <code>/bar/foo.shtml</code> and directives like <code>AddOutputFilter
    INCLUDES .shtml</code> will add the <code>INCLUDES</code> filter to the
    request. If <directive>ModMimeUsePathInfo</directive> is not set, the
    <code>INCLUDES</code> filter will not be added.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="core">AcceptPathInfo</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveCharset</name>
<description>Removes any character set associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveCharset <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>RemoveCharset is only available in Apache 2.0.24 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>RemoveCharset</directive> directive removes any
    character set associations for files with the given extensions.
    This allows <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to
    undo any associations inherited from parent directories or the
    server config files.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      RemoveCharset .html .shtml
    </example>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveEncoding</name>
<description>Removes any content encoding associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveEncoding <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>RemoveEncoding</directive> directive removes any
    encoding associations for files with the given extensions. This
    allows <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to undo
    any associations inherited from parent directories or the
    server config files. An example of its use might be:</p>

    <example><title>/foo/.htaccess:</title>
      AddEncoding x-gzip .gz<br />
      AddType text/plain .asc<br />
      &lt;Files *.gz.asc&gt;<br />
      <indent>
        RemoveEncoding .gz<br />
      </indent>
      &lt;/Files&gt;
    </example>

    <p>This will cause <code>foo.gz</code> to be marked as being
    encoded with the gzip method, but <code>foo.gz.asc</code> as an
    unencoded plaintext file.</p>

    <note><title>Note</title>
      <p><directive>RemoveEncoding</directive> directives are processed
      <em>after</em> any <directive module="mod_mime">AddEncoding</directive>
      directives, so it is possible they may undo the effects of the latter
      if both occur within the same directory configuration.</p>
    </note>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveHandler</name>
<description>Removes any handler associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveHandler <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>RemoveHandler</directive> directive removes any
    handler associations for files with the given extensions. This allows
    <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to undo any
    associations inherited from parent directories or the server
    config files. An example of its use might be:</p>

    <example><title>/foo/.htaccess:</title>
      AddHandler server-parsed .html
    </example>

    <example><title>/foo/bar/.htaccess:</title>
      RemoveHandler .html
    </example>

    <p>This has the effect of returning <code>.html</code> files in
    the <code>/foo/bar</code> directory to being treated as normal
    files, rather than as candidates for parsing (see the <module
    >mod_include</module> module).</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveInputFilter</name>
<description>Removes any input filter associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveInputFilter <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>RemoveInputFilter is only available in Apache 2.0.26 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>   
    <p>The <directive>RemoveInputFilter</directive> directive removes any
    input filter associations for files with the given extensions.
    This allows <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to
    undo any associations inherited from parent directories or the
    server config files.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="mod_mime">AddInputFilter</directive></seealso>
<seealso><directive module="core">SetInputFilter</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveLanguage</name>
<description>Removes any language associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveLanguage <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>RemoveLanguage is only available in Apache 2.0.24 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>RemoveLanguage</directive> directive removes any
    language associations for files with the given extensions. This
    allows <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to undo
    any associations inherited from parent directories or the
    server config files.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveOutputFilter</name>
<description>Removes any output filter associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveOutputFilter <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>
<compatibility>RemoveOutputFilter is only available in Apache 2.0.26 and
later.</compatibility>

<usage>    
    <p>The <directive>RemoveOutputFilter</directive> directive removes any
    output filter associations for files with the given extensions.
    This allows <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to
    undo any associations inherited from parent directories or the
    server config files.</p>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>

    <example><title>Example</title>
      RemoveOutputFilter shtml
    </example>
</usage>
<seealso><directive module="mod_mime">AddOutputFilter</directive></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>RemoveType</name>
<description>Removes any content type associations for a set of file
extensions</description>
<syntax>RemoveType <var>extension</var> [<var>extension</var>]
...</syntax>
<contextlist><context>virtual host</context><context>directory</context>
<context>.htaccess</context></contextlist>
<override>FileInfo</override>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>RemoveType</directive> directive removes any MIME
    type associations for files with the given extensions. This allows
    <code>.htaccess</code> files in subdirectories to undo any
    associations inherited from parent directories or the server
    config files. An example of its use might be:</p>

    <example><title>/foo/.htaccess:</title>
      RemoveType .cgi
    </example>

    <p>This will remove any special handling of <code>.cgi</code>
    files in the <code>/foo/</code> directory and any beneath it,
    causing the files to be treated as being of the <directive
    module="core">DefaultType</directive>.</p>

    <note><title>Note</title>
      <p><directive>RemoveType</directive> directives are processed
      <em>after</em> any <directive module="mod_mime">AddType</directive>
      directives, so it is possible they may undo the effects of the
      latter if both occur within the same directory configuration.</p>
    </note>

    <p>The <var>extension</var> argument is case-insensitive, and can
    be specified with or without a leading dot.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>TypesConfig</name>
<description>The location of the <code>mime.types</code> file</description>
<syntax>TypesConfig <var>file-path</var></syntax>
<default>TypesConfig conf/mime.types</default>
<contextlist><context>server config</context></contextlist>

<usage>
    <p>The <directive>TypesConfig</directive> directive sets the location
    of the MIME types configuration file. <var>File-path</var> is relative
    to the <directive module="core">ServerRoot</directive>. This file sets
    the default list of mappings from filename extensions to content
    types. Most administrators use the provided <code>mime.types</code>
    file, which associates common filename extensions with IANA registered
    content types. The current list is maintained at <a href=
    "http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/media-types"
    >http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/media-types</a>.
    This simplifies the <code>httpd.conf</code> file by providing the
    majority of media-type definitions, and may be overridden by
    <directive module="mod_mime">AddType</directive> directives as
    needed. You should not edit the <code>mime.types</code> file, because
    it may be replaced when you upgrade your server.</p>

    <p>The file contains lines in the format of the arguments to
    an <directive module="mod_mime">AddType</directive> directive:</p>

    <example>
      <var>MIME-type</var> [<var>extension</var>] ...
    </example>

    <p>The case of the extension does not matter. Blank lines, and lines
    beginning with a hash character (<code>#</code>) are ignored.</p>

    <note>
      Please do <strong>not</strong> send requests to the Apache HTTP
      Server Project to add any new entries in the distributed
      <code>mime.types</code> file unless (1) they are already
      registered with IANA, and (2) they use widely accepted,
      non-conflicting filename extensions across platforms.
      <code>category/x-subtype</code> requests will be automatically
      rejected, as will any new two-letter extensions as they will
      likely conflict later with the already crowded language and
      character set namespace.
    </note>
</usage>
<seealso><module>mod_mime_magic</module></seealso>
</directivesynopsis>

</modulesynopsis>
