<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE modulesynopsis SYSTEM "../style/modulesynopsis.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<modulesynopsis>

<name>mod_auth_ldap</name>
<description>Allows an LDAP directory to be used to store the database
for HTTP Basic authentication.</description>
<status>Experimental</status>
<sourcefile>mod_auth_ldap.c</sourcefile>
<identifier>auth_ldap_module</identifier>
<compatibility>Available in version 2.0.41 and later</compatibility>

<summary>
    <p><module>mod_auth_ldap</module> supports the following features:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Known to support the <a
      href="http://www.openldap.org/">OpenLDAP SDK</a> (both 1.x
      and 2.x), and the <a
      href="http://www.iplanet.com/downloads/developer/">iPlanet
      (Netscape)</a> SDK.</li>

      <li>Complex authorization policies can be implemented by
      representing the policy with LDAP filters.</li>

      <li>Support for Microsoft FrontPage allows FrontPage users to
      control access to their webs, while retaining LDAP for user
      authentication.</li>

      <li>Uses extensive caching of LDAP operations via <a
      href="mod_ldap.html">mod_ldap</a>.</li>

      <li>Support for LDAP over SSL (requires the Netscape SDK) or
      TLS (requires the OpenLDAP 2.x SDK).</li>
    </ul>
</summary>

<seealso><module>mod_ldap</module></seealso>

<section id="contents"><title>Contents</title>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="#operation">Operation</a> 

        <ul>
          <li><a href="#authenphase">The Authentication
          Phase</a></li>

          <li><a href="#authorphase">The Authorization
          Phase</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>

      <li>
        <a href="#requiredirectives">The require Directives</a> 

        <ul>
          <li><a href="#reqvaliduser">require valid-user</a></li>
          <li><a href="#requser">require user</a></li>
          <li><a href="#reqgroup">require group</a></li>
          <li><a href="#reqdn">require dn</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>

      <li><a href="#examples">Examples</a></li>
      <li><a href="#usingtls">Using TLS</a></li>
      <li><a href="#usingssl">Using SSL</a></li>

      <li>
        <a href="#frontpage">Using Microsoft FrontPage with
        <module>mod_auth_ldap</module></a> 

        <ul>
          <li><a href="#howitworks">How It Works</a></li>
          <li><a href="#fpcaveats">Caveats</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
</section>

<section id="operation"><title>Operation</title>

    <p>There are two phases in granting access to a user. The first
    phase is authentication, in which <module>mod_auth_ldap</module>
    verifies that the user's credentials are valid. This also called
    the <em>search/bind</em> phase. The second phase is
    authorization, in which <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> determines
    if the authenticated user is allowed access to the resource in
    question. This is also known as the <em>compare</em>
    phase.</p>

<section id="authenphase"><title>The Authentication
    Phase</title>

    <p>During the authentication phase, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module>
    searches for an entry in the directory that matches the username
    that the HTTP client passes. If a single unique match is found,
    then <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> attempts to bind to the
    directory server using the DN of the entry plus the password
    provided by the HTTP client. Because it does a search, then a
    bind, it is often referred to as the search/bind phase. Here are
    the steps taken during the search/bind phase.</p>

    <ol>
      <li>Generate a search filter by combining the attribute and
      filter provided in the <directive module="mod_auth_ldap"
      >AuthLDAPURL</directive> directive with
      the username passed by the HTTP client.</li>

      <li>Search the directory using the generated filter. If the
      search does not return exactly one entry, deny or decline
      access.</li>

      <li>Fetch the distinguished name of the entry retrieved from
      the search and attempt to bind to the LDAP server using the
      DN and the password passed by the HTTP client. If the bind is
      unsuccessful, deny or decline access.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>The following directives are used during the search/bind
    phase</p>

    <table>
      <tr>
        <td><directive module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPURL</directive></td>

        <td>Specifies the LDAP server, the
        base DN, the attribute to use in the search, as well as the
        extra search filter to use.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td><directive module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPBindDN</directive></td>

        <td>An optional DN to bind with
        during the search phase.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td><directive
        module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPBindPassword</directive></td>

        <td>An optional password to bind
        with during the search phase.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
</section>

<section id="authorphase"><title>The Authorization
    Phase</title>

    <p>During the authorization phase, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module>
    attempts to determine if the user is authorized to access the
    resource.  Many of these checks require
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> to do a compare operation on the
    LDAP server. This is why this phase is often referred to as the
    compare phase. <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> accepts the
    following <directive module="core">Require</directive>
    directives to determine if the credentials are acceptable:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Grant access if there is a <a href="#requser"><code>require
      valid-user</code></a> directive.</li>

      <li>Grant access if there is a <a
      href="#reqgroup"><code>require user</code></a> directive, and the
      username in the directive matches the username passed by the
      client.</li>

      <li>Grant access if there is a <a href="#reqdn"><code>require
      dn</code></a> directive, and the DN in the directive matches
      the DN fetched from the LDAP directory.</li>

      <li>Grant access if there is a <a
      href="#reqgroup"><code>require group</code></a> directive, and
      the DN fetched from the LDAP directory (or the username
      passed by the client) occurs in the LDAP group.</li>

      <li>otherwise, deny or decline access</li>
    </ul>

    <p><module>mod_auth_ldap</module> uses the following directives during the
    compare phase:</p>

    <table>
      <tr>
        <td><directive module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPURL</directive> </td>

        <td>The attribute specified in the
        URL is used in compare operations for the <code>require
        user</code> operation.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td><directive
        module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPCompareDNOnServer</directive></td>

        <td>Determines the behavior of the
        <code>require dn</code> directive.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td><directive
        module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPGroupAttribute</directive></td>

        <td>Determines the attribute to
        use for comparisons in the <code>require group</code>
        directive.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td><directive
        module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPGroupAttributeIsDN</directive></td>

        <td>Specifies whether to use the
        user DN or the username when doing comparisons for the
        <code>require group</code> directive.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
</section>
</section>

<section id="requiredirectives"><title>The require Directives</title>

    <p>Apache's <directive module="core">Require</directive>
    directives are used during the authorization phase to ensure that
    a user is allowed to access a resource.</p>

<section id="reqvaliduser"><title>require
    valid-user</title>

    <p>If this directive exists, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> grants
    access to any user that has successfully authenticated during the
    search/bind phase.</p>
</section>

<section id="requser"><title>require user</title>

    <p>The <code>require user</code> directive specifies what
    usernames can access the resource. Once
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> has retrieved a unique DN from the
    directory, it does an LDAP compare operation using the username
    specified in the <code>require user</code> to see if that username
    is part of the just-fetched LDAP entry.  Multiple users can be
    granted access by putting multiple usernames on the line,
    separated with spaces. If a username has a space in it, then it
    must be the only user on the line. In this case, multiple users
    can be granted access by using multiple <code>require user</code>
    directives, with one user per line. For example, with a <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPURL</directive> of
    <code>ldap://ldap/o=Airius?cn</code> (i.e., <code>cn</code> is
    used for searches), the following require directives could be used
    to restrict access:</p>
<example>
require user Barbara Jenson<br />
require user Fred User<br />
require user Joe Manager<br />
</example>

    <p>Because of the way that <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> handles this
    directive, Barbara Jenson could sign on as <em>Barbara
    Jenson</em>, <em>Babs Jenson</em> or any other <code>cn</code> that
    she has in her LDAP entry. Only the single <code>require
    user</code> line is needed to support all values of the attribute
    in the user's entry.</p>

    <p>If the <code>uid</code> attribute was used instead of the
    <code>cn</code> attribute in the URL above, the above three lines
    could be condensed to</p>
<example>require user bjenson fuser jmanager</example>
</section>

<section id="reqgroup"><title>require group</title>

    <p>This directive specifies an LDAP group whose members are
    allowed access. It takes the distinguished name of the LDAP
    group. For example, assume that the following entry existed in
    the LDAP directory:</p>
<example>
dn: cn=Administrators, o=Airius<br />
objectClass: groupOfUniqueNames<br />
uniqueMember: cn=Barbara Jenson, o=Airius<br />
uniqueMember: cn=Fred User, o=Airius<br />
</example>

    <p>The following directive would grant access to both Fred and
    Barbara:</p>
<example>require group cn=Administrators, o=Airius</example>

    <p>Behavior of this directive is modified by the <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPGroupAttribute</directive> and
    <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPGroupAttributeIsDN</directive>
    directives.</p>
</section>

<section id="reqdn"><title>require dn</title>

    <p>The <code>require dn</code> directive allows the administrator
    to grant access based on distinguished names. It specifies a DN
    that must match for access to be granted. If the distinguished
    name that was retrieved from the directory server matches the
    distinguished name in the <code>require dn</code>, then
    authorization is granted.</p>

    <p>The following directive would grant access to a specific
    DN:</p>
<example>require dn cn=Barbara Jenson, o=Airius</example>

    <p>Behavior of this directive is modified by the <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPCompareDNOnServer</directive>
    directive.</p>
</section>
</section>

<section id="examples"><title>Examples</title>

    <ul>
      <li>
        Grant access to anyone who exists in the LDAP directory,
        using their UID for searches. 
<example>
AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap1.airius.com:389/ou=People, o=Airius?uid?sub?(objectClass=*)<br />
require valid-user
</example>
      </li>

      <li>
        The next example is the same as above; but with the fields
        that have useful defaults omitted. Also, note the use of a
        redundant LDAP server. 
<example>AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap1.airius.com ldap2.airius.com/ou=People, o=Airius<br />
require valid-user
</example>
      </li>

      <li>
        The next example is similar to the previous one, but is
        uses the common name instead of the UID. Note that this
        could be problematical if multiple people in the directory
        share the same <code>cn</code>, because a search on <code>cn</code>
        <strong>must</strong> return exactly one entry. That's why
        this approach is not recommended: it's a better idea to
        choose an attribute that is guaranteed unique in your
        directory, such as <code>uid</code>. 
<example>
AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap.airius.com/ou=People, o=Airius?cn<br />
require valid-user
</example>
      </li>

      <li>
        Grant access to anybody in the Administrators group. The
        users must authenticate using their UID. 
<example>
AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap.airius.com/o=Airius?uid<br />
require group cn=Administrators, o=Airius
</example>
      </li>

      <li>
        The next example assumes that everyone at Airius who
        carries an alphanumeric pager will have an LDAP attribute
        of <code>qpagePagerID</code>. The example will grant access
        only to people (authenticated via their UID) who have
        alphanumeric pagers: 
<example>
AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap.airius.com/o=Airius?uid??(qpagePagerID=*)<br />
require valid-user
</example>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>The next example demonstrates the power of using filters
        to accomplish complicated administrative requirements.
        Without filters, it would have been necessary to create a
        new LDAP group and ensure that the group's members remain
        synchronized with the pager users. This becomes trivial
        with filters. The goal is to grant access to anyone who has
        a filter, plus grant access to Joe Manager, who doesn't
        have a pager, but does need to access the same
        resource:</p>
<example>
AuthLDAPURL ldap://ldap.airius.com/o=Airius?uid??(|(qpagePagerID=*)(uid=jmanager))<br />
require valid-user
</example>

        <p>This last may look confusing at first, so it helps to
        evaluate what the search filter will look like based on who
        connects, as shown below. The text in blue is the part that
        is filled in using the attribute specified in the URL. The
        text in red is the part that is filled in using the filter
        specified in the URL. The text in green is filled in using
        the information that is retrieved from the HTTP client. If
        Fred User connects as <code>fuser</code>, the filter would look
        like</p>

        <example>(&amp;(|(qpagePagerID=*)(uid=jmanager))(uid=fuser))</example>

        <p>The above search will only succeed if <em>fuser</em> has a
        pager. When Joe Manager connects as <em>jmanager</em>, the
        filter looks like</p>

        <example>(&amp;(|(qpagePagerID=*)(uid=jmanager))(uid=jmanager))</example>

        <p>The above search will succeed whether <em>jmanager</em>
        has a pager or not.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
</section>

<section id="usingtls"><title>Using TLS</title>

    <p>To use TLS, simply set the <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPStartTLS</directive> to on.
    Nothing else needs to be done (other than ensure that your LDAP
    server is configured for TLS).</p>
</section>

<section id="usingssl"><title>Using SSL</title>

    <p>If <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> is linked against the
    Netscape/iPlanet LDAP SDK, it will not talk to any SSL server
    unless that server has a certificate signed by a known Certificate
    Authority. As part of the configuration
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> needs to be told where it can find
    a database containing the known CAs. This database is in the same
    format as Netscape Communicator's <code>cert7.db</code>
    database. The easiest way to get this file is to start up a fresh
    copy of Netscape, and grab the resulting
    <code>$HOME/.netscape/cert7.db</code> file.</p>

    <p>To specify a secure LDAP server, use <em>ldaps://</em> in the
    <directive module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPURL</directive>
    directive, instead of <em>ldap://</em>.</p>
</section>

<section id="frontpage"><title>Using Microsoft
    FrontPage with mod_auth_ldap</title>

    <p>Normally, FrontPage uses FrontPage-web-specific user/group
    files (i.e., the <module>mod_authn_file</module> and
    <module>mod_authz_groupfile</module> modules) to handle all
    authentication. Unfortunately, it is not possible to just
    change to LDAP authentication by adding the proper directives,
    because it will break the <em>Permissions</em> forms in
    the FrontPage client, which attempt to modify the standard
    text-based authorization files.</p>

    <p>Once a FrontPage web has been created, adding LDAP
    authentication to it is a matter of adding the following
    directives to <em>every</em> <code>.htaccess</code> file
    that gets created in the web</p>
<example><pre>
AuthLDAPURL            the url
AuthLDAPAuthoritative  off
AuthLDAPFrontPageHack  on
</pre></example>

    <p><directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPAuthoritative</directive> must be
    off to allow <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> to decline group
    authentication so that Apache will fall back to file
    authentication for checking group membership. This allows the
    FrontPage-managed group file to be used.</p>

<section id="howitworks"><title>How It Works</title>

    <p>FrontPage restricts access to a web by adding the <code>require
    valid-user</code> directive to the <code>.htaccess</code>
    files. If <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPFrontPageHack</directive> is not
    on, the <code>require valid-user</code> directive will succeed for
    any user who is valid <em>as far as LDAP is
    concerned</em>. This means that anybody who has an entry in
    the LDAP directory is considered a valid user, whereas FrontPage
    considers only those people in the local user file to be
    valid. The purpose of the hack is to force Apache to consult the
    local user file (which is managed by FrontPage) - instead of LDAP
    - when handling the <code>require valid-user</code> directive.</p>

    <p>Once directives have been added as specified above,
    FrontPage users will be able to perform all management
    operations from the FrontPage client.</p>
</section>

<section id="fpcaveats"><title>Caveats</title>

    <ul>
      <li>When choosing the LDAP URL, the attribute to use for
      authentication should be something that will also be valid
      for putting into a <module>mod_authn_file</module> user file.
      The user ID is ideal for this.</li>

      <li>When adding users via FrontPage, FrontPage administrators
      should choose usernames that already exist in the LDAP
      directory (for obvious reasons). Also, the password that the
      administrator enters into the form is ignored, since Apache
      will actually be authenticating against the password in the
      LDAP database, and not against the password in the local user
      file. This could cause confusion for web administrators.</li>

      <!-- XXX is that true? was mod_auth before the aaa change -->
      <li>Apache must be compiled with <module>mod_auth_basic</module>,
      <module>mod_authn_file</module> and
      <module>mod_authz_groupfile</module> in order to
      use FrontPage support. This is because Apache will still use
      the <module>mod_authz_groupfile</module> group file for determine the extent of a
      user's access to the FrontPage web.</li>

      <li>The directives must be put in the <code>.htaccess</code>
      files. Attempting to put them inside <directive module="core"
      type="section">Location</directive> or <directive module="core"
      type="section">Directory</directive> directives won't work. This
      is because <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> has to be able to grab
      the <directive module="mod_authn_file">AuthUserFile</directive>
      directive that is found in FrontPage <code>.htaccess</code>
      files so that it knows where to look for the valid user list. If
      the <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> directives aren't in the same
      <code>.htaccess</code> file as the FrontPage directives, then
      the hack won't work, because <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will
      never get a chance to process the <code>.htaccess</code> file,
      and won't be able to find the FrontPage-managed user file.</li>
    </ul>
</section>
</section>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPAuthoritative</name>
<description>Prevent other authentication modules from
authenticating the user if this one fails</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPAuthoritative on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPAuthoritative on</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>Set to <code>off</code> if this module should let other
    authentication modules attempt to authenticate the user, should
    authentication with this module fail. Control is only passed on
    to lower modules if there is no DN or rule that matches the
    supplied user name (as passed by the client).</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPBindDN</name>
<description>Optional DN to use in binding to the LDAP server</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPBindDN <em>distinguished-name</em></syntax>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>An optional DN used to bind to the server when searching for
    entries. If not provided, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will use
    an anonymous bind.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPBindPassword</name>
<description>Password used in conjuction with the bind DN</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPBindPassword <em>password</em></syntax>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>A bind password to use in conjunction with the bind DN. Note
    that the bind password is probably sensitive data, and should be
    properly protected. You should only use the <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPBindDN</directive> and <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPBindPassword</directive> if you
    absolutely need them to search the directory.</p> 
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPCompareDNOnServer</name>
<description>Use the LDAP server to compare the DNs</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPCompareDNOnServer on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPCompareDNOnServer on</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>When set, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will use the LDAP
    server to compare the DNs. This is the only foolproof way to
    compare DNs.  <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will search the
    directory for the DN specified with the <a
    href="#reqdn"><code>require dn</code></a> directive, then,
    retrieve the DN and compare it with the DN retrieved from the user
    entry. If this directive is not set,
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> simply does a string comparison. It
    is possible to get false negatives with this approach, but it is
    much faster. Note the <module>mod_ldap</module> cache can speed up
    DN comparison in most situations.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPDereferenceAliases</name>
<description>When will the module de-reference aliases</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPDereferenceAliases never|searching|finding|always</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPDereferenceAliases Always</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>This directive specifies when <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will
    de-reference aliases during LDAP operations. The default is
    <code>always</code>.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPEnabled</name>
<description>Turn on or off LDAP authentication</description>
<syntax> AuthLDAPEnabled on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPEnabled on</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>Set to <code>off</code> to disable
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> in certain directories. This is
    useful if you have <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> enabled at or
    near the top of your tree, but want to disable it completely in
    certain locations.</p> 
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPFrontPageHack</name>
<description>Allow LDAP authentication to work with MS FrontPage</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPFrontPageHack on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPFronPageHack off</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>See the section on <a href="#frontpage">using Microsoft
    FrontPage</a> with <module>mod_auth_ldap</module>.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPGroupAttribute</name>
<description>LDAP attributes used to check for group membership</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPGroupAttribute <em>attribute</em></syntax>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>This directive specifies which LDAP attributes are used to
    check for group membership. Multiple attributes can be used by
    specifying this directive multiple times. If not specified,
    then <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> uses the <code>member</code> and
    <code>uniquemember</code> attributes.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPGroupAttributeIsDN</name>
<description>Use the DN of the client username when checking for
group membership</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPGroupAttributeIsDN on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPGroupAttributeIsDN on</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>When set <code>on</code>, this directive says to use the
    distinguished name of the client username when checking for group
    membership.  Otherwise, the username will be used. For example,
    assume that the client sent the username <code>bjenson</code>,
    which corresponds to the LDAP DN <code>cn=Babs Jenson,
    o=Airius</code>. If this directive is set,
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will check if the group has
    <code>cn=Babs Jenson, o=Airius</code> as a member. If this
    directive is not set, then <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will
    check if the group has <code>bjenson</code> as a member.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPRemoteUserIsDN</name>
<description>Use the DN of the client username to set the REMOTE_USER
environment variable</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPRemoteUserIsDN on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPUserIsDN off</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>If this directive is set to on, the value of the
    <code>REMOTE_USER</code> environment variable will be set to the full
    distinguished name of the authenticated user, rather than just
    the username that was passed by the client. It is turned off by
    default.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPStartTLS</name>
<description>Use a secure TLS connection to the LDAP server</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPStartTLS on|off</syntax>
<default>AuthLDAPStartTLS off</default>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>If this directive is set to <code>on</code>,
    <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will start a secure TLS session
    after connecting to the LDAP server. This requires your LDAP
    server to support TLS.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

<directivesynopsis>
<name>AuthLDAPUrl</name>
<description>URL specifying the LDAP search parameters</description>
<syntax>AuthLDAPUrl <em>url</em></syntax>
<contextlist><context>directory</context><context>.htaccess</context>
</contextlist>
<override>AuthConfig</override>

<usage>
    <p>An RFC 2255 URL which specifies the LDAP search parameters
    to use. The syntax of the URL is</p>
<example>ldap://host:port/basedn?attribute?scope?filter</example>

<dl>
<dt>ldap</dt>

        <dd>For regular ldap, use the
        string <code>ldap</code>. For secure LDAP, use <code>ldaps</code>
        instead. Secure LDAP is only available if Apache was linked
        to an LDAP library with SSL support.</dd>

<dt>host:port</dt>

        <dd>
          <p>The name/port of the ldap server (defaults to
          <code>localhost:389</code> for <code>ldap</code>, and
          <code>localhost:636</code> for <code>ldaps</code>). To
          specify multiple, redundant LDAP servers, just list all
          servers, separated by spaces. <module>mod_auth_ldap</module>
          will try connecting to each server in turn, until it makes a
          successful connection.</p>

          <p>Once a connection has been made to a server, that
          connection remains active for the life of the
          <code>httpd</code> process, or until the LDAP server goes
          down.</p>

          <p>If the LDAP server goes down and breaks an existing
          connection, <module>mod_auth_ldap</module> will attempt to
          re-connect, starting with the primary server, and trying
          each redundant server in turn. Note that this is different
          than a true round-robin search.</p>
        </dd>

<dt>basedn</dt>

        <dd>The DN of the branch of the
        directory where all searches should start from. At the very
        least, this must be the top of your directory tree, but
        could also specify a subtree in the directory.</dd>

<dt>attribute</dt>

        <dd>The attribute to search for.
        Although RFC 2255 allows a comma-separated list of
        attributes, only the first attribute will be used, no
        matter how many are provided. If no attributes are
        provided, the default is to use <code>uid</code>. It's a good
        idea to choose an attribute that will be unique across all
        entries in the subtree you will be using.</dd>

<dt>scope</dt>

        <dd>The scope of the search. Can be either <code>one</code> or
        <code>sub</code>. Note that a scope of <code>base</code> is
        also supported by RFC 2255, but is not supported by this
        module. If the scope is not provided, or if <code>base</code> scope
        is specified, the default is to use a scope of
        <code>sub</code>.</dd>

<dt>filter</dt>

        <dd>A valid LDAP search filter. If
        not provided, defaults to <code>(objectClass=*)</code>, which
        will search for all objects in the tree. Filters are
        limited to approximately 8000 characters (the definition of
        <code>MAX_STRING_LEN</code> in the Apache source code). This
        should be than sufficient for any application.</dd>
</dl>

    <p>When doing searches, the attribute, filter and username passed
    by the HTTP client are combined to create a search filter that
    looks like
    <code>(&amp;(<em>filter</em>)(<em>attribute</em>=<em>username</em>))</code>.</p>

    <p>For example, consider an URL of
    <code>ldap://ldap.airius.com/o=Airius?cn?sub?(posixid=*)</code>. When
    a client attempts to connect using a username of <code>Babs
    Jenson</code>, the resulting search filter will be
    <code>(&amp;(posixid=*)(cn=Babs Jenson))</code>.</p>

    <p>See above for examples of <directive
    module="mod_auth_ldap">AuthLDAPURL</directive> URLs.</p>
</usage>
</directivesynopsis>

</modulesynopsis>
