<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE manualpage SYSTEM "../style/manualpage.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../style/manual.en.xsl"?>
<!-- $LastChangedRevision$ -->

<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<manualpage metafile="index.xml.meta">
<parentdocument href="../"/>

<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<summary>
    <p>This document is not a traditional FAQ, but rather a quick
    guide showing you what to do when you run into problems with the
    Apache HTTP Server.</p>

    <p>A more traditional but quite outdated document is the <a
    href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/misc/FAQ.html">Apache 1.3
    FAQ</a>.</p> 
</summary>

    <section id="support.what2do">
    <title>"Why can't I ...? Why won't ... work?" What to do in case of
    problems</title>

      <p>If you are having trouble with your Apache server software, you should
      take the following steps:</p>

      <dl>
      <dt>Check the ErrorLog!</dt>
      <dd><p>Apache tries to be helpful when it encounters a problem. In many
      cases, it will provide some details by writing one or more messages to the
      server error log. Sometimes this is enough for you to diagnose and fix
      the problem yourself (such as file permissions or the like). The default
      location of the error log is
      <code>/usr/local/apache2/logs/error_log</code>, but see the <directive
      module="core">ErrorLog</directive> directive in your config files for the
      location on your server.</p>

      <p>If you end up in any of the support forums this is quite likely to be the
      first place they will ask you retrieve information from.  Please ensure you
      know where to find your errorlog.  If you are unsure, the wiki page
      <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/httpd/DistrosDefaultLayout"> here</a> can
      give you some ideas where to look.</p></dd>

      <dt>Consult the wiki</dt>
      <dd>The <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/httpd/">Apache HTTP
      Server Wiki</a> contains guides to solving many common
      problems.</dd>

      <dt>Check the Apache bug database</dt> <dd>Most problems that
      get reported to The Apache Group are recorded in the <a
      href="http://httpd.apache.org/bug_report.html">bug database</a>.
      <strong>Do not</strong> submit a new bug report until you have
      checked existing reports (open <em>and</em> closed) and asked
      about your problem in a user-support forum (see below). If you
      find that your issue has already been reported, please
      <em>don't</em> add a "me, too" report.</dd>

      <dt><a id="support.what2do.user-support"
      name="support.what2do.user-support">Ask in a user support forum</a></dt>
      <dd><p>Apache has an active community of users who are willing to share
      their knowledge. Participating in this community is usually the best and
      fastest way to get answers to your questions and problems.</p>

      <p><a href="http://httpd.apache.org/userslist.html">Users
      mailing list</a></p>

      <p><a href="irc://irc.freenode.net/#httpd">#httpd</a> on 
      <a href="http://freenode.net">Freenode IRC</a> is also available for 
      user support issues.</p>
      </dd>

      <dt>Please use the bug database for bugs!</dt>
      <dd><p>If you've gone through those steps above that are appropriate and
      have obtained no relief, then please <em>do</em> let the httpd developers
      know about the problem by <a
      href="http://httpd.apache.org/bug_report.html">logging a bug
      report</a>.</p>

      <p>If your problem involves the server crashing and generating a core
      dump, please <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/dev/debugging.html">
      include a backtrace</a> (if possible).</p>
      </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section id="support.support"><title>Whom do I contact for support?</title>
      <p>With millions of users and fewer than sixty volunteer developers,
      we cannot provide personal support for Apache. For free support, we
      suggest participating in a user forum (see above).</p>

      <p>Professional, commercial support for Apache is available from
      a number of companies.</p>
    </section>

</manualpage>
